Итак, мы находимся в моей гостиной
в Токио, в Японии. И я собираюсь всем показать
какая это классная штука — Биткоин.
Сейчас я отправлю 100 евро в Биткоинах
через телевизор, с помощью камеры
на другой телевизор в Нидерландах,
и любой человек с Биткоин-кошельком
прямо сейчас сможет получить
этот перевод.
Мы собираемся получить
100 евро в Биткоинах и
никто не сможет нам запретить это
или заморозить счёт, заблокировать или
или контролировать его. Здесь на экране ТВ
показан Биткоин-адрес, который
я только что создал. И с помощью телефона я
сосканирую QR-код адреса с экрана.
Готово.
Теперь я посылаю эквивалент ста евро
На этот адресу. Нажимаю «послать»
и любой может отслеживать баланс этого адреса
на blockchain.info. Вот он.
Смотрите, на экране, 100 евро в биткоинах
только что дошли до адреса. Таким образом,
в сумме получено 100 евро, конечный баланс, 100
евро, все просто. На следующем экране
вы увидите, как любой человек
с Биткоин-кошельком сосканирует
секретный ключ, соответствующий данному адресу,
сможет истратить
эти деньги, только лишь просканировав
код на мониторе своего ТВ.
Взгляните, вот они, 100 евро,
готовые к выдаче.
Все, что нужно сделать просканировать
вот здесь. И вот они биткоины
эквивалентные 100 евро на сегодняшний день,
а может уже и
больше.
Вот, в принципе, всё что нужно для
желающих работать с биткоинами.
Итак, Голландия, ты только что увидела
мощь Биткоина. Я послал биткоины
на 100 евро отсюда из Токио
напрямую Вам ребята через камеру,
через сеть, через ТВ
к вам домой. Если бы я попытался это сделать,
используя обычный банк, это
бы заняло несколько дней
и, вероятно, перевод бы стоил 30 евро. Но я это
сделал с помощью Биткоина,
в общем бесплатно, и мне не пришлось
спрашивать у кого-то разрешения. Мне не понадобился
Банк. Мне не понадобилось правительство.
Мне никто не понадобился. Только я,
ты и наши смартфоны.
Вот в чём преимущетсво Биткоина.
Это Backlight. Добро пожаловать в мир, где
каждый сможет быть банком.
Мы привыкли, что выпуск денег
контролируется государством
и банками, но существует группа
людей, для которых это не данность,
которые задумываются и работают над этим.
Уолл Стрит — мошенничество, Америка — мошенничество,
мир — обманщик, банки — обманщики,
центральные банки — обманщики. Мы живем в эру
мошенничества. Всё основывается на обмане.
Они получают свой процент от обмана.
Это бизнес модель. Даже если предположить,
что есть хоть какой-то морально-этический
аспект в том, что сейчас происходит,
было бы наивно отрицать,
что мы живем в эпоху
финансовых террористов. Террористы,
террористы, террористы, банковские джехадисты.
Они пришли убить вас и себя.
Они верят в идеологию, не в Коран,
а в Адама Смита, которого
совершенно неверно истолковывают
и интерпретируют как нечто, оправдывающее
их действия.
[неразборчивая речь] — террорист
[неразборчивая речь] — террорист, ЦБ Японии —
террорист. Все они настоящие
террористы.
Перевод принят. Данное сообщество
работает, с их точки зрения, над улучшенной
монетарной системой; системой, где банки не нужны,
поскольку платежи
можно совершать напрямую от одного
человека другому. В кредитной системе,
одна из двух сторон, всегда в рабстве.
И это денежная структура, в которой мы живем.
Архитектура денег, используемая
цивилизацией — это система,
в которой у тебя нет контроля,
система, где любое взаимодействие
включает третью сторону,
этоа третья сторона имеет полный контроль
над деньгами. Биткоин совершенно
отличается, потому что здесь вы никому ничего
не должны и вам никто не должен.
Это отличная от банковской система.
Она основывается на владении,
и никто это запретить, упразднить или
заморозить
не может. Но они скажут, что
они обеспокоены,
очень обеспокоены. Обеспокоены, что преступники
воспользуются биткоинами. Но, правда
глубже, они обеспокоены тем,
что этой системой воспользуемся все мы. Спасибо.
Биткоин, криптовалюта, более всего
известная как удобный инструмент для
преступников, неожиданно стала
важной темой на конференциях
по финансовым инновациям во всём мире.
Сторонники страстно рассказывают
о цифровом чуде, которое спасет мир
от финансового краха. История Биткоинов
начиналась как религиозное откровение.
2 Ноября, 2008, шесть недель спустя после
краха банка Lehman Brothers.
Весь мир был в панике, обсуждая
как спасать банки. Тогда
на одном малопосещаемом интернет форуме
криптографов появился документ, предлагающий
абсолютно новую монетарную систему.
Автор этой системы называл
себя Сатоши Накамото.
— Впервые я услышал об этом в Техасе
от друга. Мы обедали и он сказал
«Чувак, появились новые сумасшедшие деньги»,
и весь обед он говорил об этом,
придя домой, я говорил себе: «Черт, я хочу —
хочу посмотреть смогу ли купить немного этих денег»,
Я захотел купить немного.
Я написал e-mail своему другу. Я думаю,
вероятно, я прочитал статью в электронном виде
или как-то. Знаете, в ней было
сказано о новой электронной валюте.
Всё это было в открытом доступе. Знаете,
это было опубликовано,
дайте подумать, декабрь, 2008,
или что-то около. Это были тяжелейшие
дни финансового кризиса. Всё это
натолкнуло меня на светлую мысль. Мысль
о возможности, идеальной возможности,
представить новую радикальную технологию
и новый подход к деньгам,
в самый подходящий момент, когда
люди  открыты совершить этот скачок.
Миру требовалось принять новую
валюту. Я вполне уверен, что
Сатоши это реальный человек,
хотя было бы прикольно, если бы это был ИИ.
Но на 99.99% — он реальный человек.
Что меня волнует, так это мировая экономика.
Сейчас, мы говорим,
что у нас есть глобальная экономика,
но я не могу взять доллар и передать его
тебе в Голландию, и что придётся с ним
делать? Придётся идти и
обменять его на твою национальную валюту.
А если мы пропустим этот шаг —
я просто посылаю некое платежное средство,
в обмен на товар за считанные секунды —
это сильно изменит
весь мир.
Моя первая покупка была
на 25 000 $, в 2011 году и цена биткоина
была около 1$. Я продолжал
покупать Биткоины. И каждый раз,
желая заработать пару долларов
для моей другой компании, я вкладывал в Биткоины.
Поэтому большинство моих
доходов я держу в Биткоинах.
И держу до сих пор. Рад, что вы не
платили за парковку. Машина на самом деле
отличная тема для Биткоин.
Мы хотим заказать трафарет Биткоина
и делать логотипы на автомобилях
И разъезжать на них по Токио,
в надежде, что это поможет
разрекламировать биткоины, но пока
не дошли до этого руки, может когда-нибудь.
Роджер Вер, исполнительный директор MemoryDealers.com,
продает комплектующие для б/у компьютеров.
Но уже несколько лет
он известен как Биткойн Иисус.
В 2011 году он купил биткоинов на 25 000$,
которые сейчас оцениваются рынком в
6 млн долларов. А, кто-то закрыл мой...
обычно оставляю капот
приоткрытым, чтобы я смог присоединить
аккумулятор, не знаю почему
кто-то закрыл, пока меня
не было. Поэтому, нам нужно…
Некоторые думают, что Биткоин — это для
тех кто успел, «Окей, я уже опоздал»
или «Не будет ли проблем с Биткоином?»
Думать так  «не поздно ли включаться
в эту систему» всё равно, что думать
«не поздно ли начать
пользоваться интернетом» или
«не поздно ли использовать
мобильный телефон»?
Биткоин во многих отношениях
упростит вашу жизнь, а что касаемо
стоимости Биткоинов —
тем более не поздно.
Цена Биткоина сейчас 270$.
Если Биткоин станет очень популярен
во всем мире, то его цена будет
исчисляться как минимум
тесятками тысяч долларов,
если не сотнями тысяч
долларов за 1 Биткоин. Поэтому
думать, что слишком поздно
включаться — всё равно, что
думать, что поздно начинать
пользоваться Интернетом. Конечно,
Биткоины ещё не повсеместно используются,
но однажды
это случится.
Совершенные деньги, должны иметь ограниченный
выпуск, это одно из главных
условий. Деньги нуждаются в этом условии,
они должны быть узнаваемы, надежны,
подвижны.
В Биткойне выполнены эти
условия лучше, чем в других
известных валютах. Поэтому столкнувшись
в первый раз с Биткойнами я осознал,
насколько они невероятно полезны,
и люди будут ими пользоваться
больше и больше.
Роджер живет и работает в Токио.
Всю работу в своей компании
он передал на аутсорс, поэтому может тратить
всё время на раскрутку Биткоин.
Сейчас захватывающее время, особенно
из-за с ситуации в Греции.
Имею в виду, что цена Биткойна за день
подросла на 10$. Из-за новостей
о греческом референдуме цена Биткоина
каждый день растет. Можно видеть
большое число сделок за
последние 24 часа. Я заплатил
за установку рекламного щита
прямо в сердце Кремниевой Долины,
там написан слоган:
«Принимаем Биткоины, MemoryDealers.com»,
а затем список комплектующих,
которые мы продаем. Потом, я стал оплачивать
рекламу на национальном радио США,
чтобы охватить сотни
радиостанций по всей Америке и оплачивал её
несколько лет подряд. Ок.
Wave — популярный потребительский сайт
в Японии — уже принимает к оплате Биткоины.
На пресс конференции Роджер Вер помогает
им нести слово Биткойново.
Сегодня Биткоин стоит 35 000 йен.
Если Биткоины станут популярны во всем мире,
то однозначно цена вырастет до миллионов
или десятков миллионов.
Роджер сейчас нам это объяснит.
Роджер, скажи, что такого
особенного в Биткоинах?
Здесь сказано, что значит «хорошие деньги»,
но Натали лучше меня говорит по-японски.
Это трудно объяснить.
Хотите это сделать?
На экране вы видите
несколько особенностей Биткоина.
К примеру, нет затрат на переводы.
Они прозрачны и открыты.
Самое важное, что положительные
особенности денег
укрепятся ещё.
Деньги, которыми мы пользовались
до Биткоина обладают некоторми
из этих особенностей.
Но впервые в истории
сейчас у нас есть Биткоин.
В нём соединились лучшие качества денег,
и он станет лучшей валютой в мире.
У кого есть Биткоин-кошелек?
Я прямо сейчас вышлю вам денег.
— Перевел. Уже получены. Быстро, не так ли?
— Да, уже поступили.
— Менее чем за 5 секунд.
— Да, быстро.
— Если вы скачаете приложение.. уже перевели?
— Уже поступили, да?
Сейчас цена биткоина — 1000 йен,
если он станет популярным
цена может увеличиться до миллиона.
— Роджер, ты раздаешь Биткоины?
— Я даю любому желающему
биткоины на сумму 1000 йен, что
примерно равно 8$ и несколько центов.
— Окей.
Я посылал тысячи биткоинов
разным людям, присылавшим свои адреса
на Фейсбуке, и это было,
когда биткоин стоил пару долларов.
Сейчас я уверен, что эти люди
вполне счастливы.
Как же эти электронные деньги, придуманные
Сатоши Накамото, стали в сотни раз
более ценными, чем доллар, и почему
энтузиасты, такие как Роджер Вер,
хотят перевести весь мир
на Биткоины. Чтобы это понять, давайте
посмотрим, как создаются новые Биткоины.
Этот сложный процесс называется майнинг.
Промо видео выглядят так, словно
любой человек может добыть Биткоины.
Миллоны людей ежедневно получают
эту криптовалюту. Все достаточно просто,
скачиваете специальное программное обеспечение,
подсоединяетесь к интернету, и ждёте
когда прибыль начнет расти.
Для майнинга не нужны специальные знания,
это можно делать дома, на работе, в кафе —
везде, где есть интернет-доступ. И, кстати,
много людей уже получили неплохой
доход от майнинга. Как интересно,
придется ли нам — придётся ли тебе вылезать
утром из кровати, нет, не придется. А?
Не придется вылезать из кровати рано
утром. Нет, не придется. Я понял. Маршал
Лонг был одним из первых в мире
майнеров. Сейчас он исполнительный директор
FinalHash — компании, профессионально
добывающей Биткоины. Окей. Здорово.
Обсудим это подробнее в Чикаго. Договорились.
— Спасибо.
В начале своего пути, знаете,
мне звонили мои друзья, «О, чувак,
я потерял 10 000 Биткоинов, потому что
мой компьютер подвис». На тот момент
Биткоин стоил меньше одного цента.
Понимаете, никому не было дела, что
они потеряли 10 долларов. Сейчас
10 000 Биткоинов стоят 5 миллионов долларов.
Это совершенно другие деньги, правильно?
И интересно заметить,
как изменилась эта индустрия.
Тогда не было каналов на Ютюбе, где
учили как майнить, и у меня заняло
около трёх недель, чтобы подключить
к этому всему компьютер и научиться
майнить. В те дни
можно было взять вот такой ноутбук
и намайнить может 100 или
200 монет в день.
Когда лето пришло в Хьюстон,
жена сказала: «слушай,
кондиционер проработал сутки.
Но здесь очень жарко.
Чем ты занимался?» Я ответил:
«Знаешь, здесь работали несколько
компьютеров одновременно».
Когда она увидела
50 видеокарт, работающих одновременно
ей тоже стало жарко.
«Окей, тебе надо отсюда выбираться.
Тебе нужно отвлечься, потому что
тут жара». Эй, привет Нерд Кейвс и Фанаты?
Здесь Джерри по прозвищу
Барнакула. Здесь со мной Маршалл Лонг
из FinalHash. И мы здесь, чтобы
создать самой большой проект по
майнингу Биткоинов в Северной Америке.
Это на самом деле реальная операция
по майнингу и вы сможете увидеть всё,
что здесь будет происходить.
— Это золотой рудник.
— На самом деле добыча
золота. У нас есть мощное
оборудование. У нас есть затраты.
Затраты на энергию.
— Да.
— И средства восстановления.
— Всё верно.
И всё это мы продадим и превратим
в реальные деньги.
— Всё правильно.
Окей. Сколько здесь этих аппаратов?
Ты получаешь S4 и S5 каждый день.
— На самом деле, кажется, что здесь в основном S4.
— В основном S4 и есть.
Это буквально самое шумное место из всех.
Это как стоять в аэродинамической трубе.
Выдуваем вверх. Эти штуки выбрасывают потоки воздуха
и охлаждение здесь очень эффективно. Если
просунешь руку за эти юниты,
то почувствуешь сильный холод.
Здесь входит ледяной воздух.
Если приложить руку к передней части
по центру, то там
невероятно печёт, очень жарко.
Подумай, выгодно ли майнить в таком масштабе?
Чёрт, конечно, да.
Биткоин — это вознаграждение за решение
сложных математических задач
и майнеры заставляют свои компьютеры работать
круглосуточно, чтобы решить эти задачи.
Пользователи Биткоина во всём мире
соединены вместе в одну сеть,
в которой происходят и проверяются
все транзакции, попадающие в общий реестр —
блокчейн. И Сатоши Накамото
создал её таким образом,
чтобы пользователи могли свободно и
и анонимно создавать цифровые счета — кошельки.
Изобретение Сатоши упразднило
необходимость в центральном банке, потому что
все пользователи вместе и есть банк. Конечно
в начале пользователи и не подозревали
насколько вырастут и биткоин, и блокчейн.
Мне кажется, что весной 2010, могу ошибиться
с точными датами, кто-то прислал запрос,
«Эй, я бы
хотел купить что-то за Биткоины.
Кто-нибудь купит мне пиццу?»  И
кто-то здесь в Англии купил
человеку во Флориде пиццу за примерно
10 000 Биткоинов.
Это большая сумма денег по нынешним временам.
И это был первый факт коммерческого
использования Биткоинов. Гаррик Хилеман,
экономист Лондонской Школы Экономики,
был первым ученым, кто стал изучать
Биткоины и Блокчейн как серьезную
денежную систему.
— Как ученый, вы уже сталкивались
с подобным, или это совершенно новая для Вас тема?
— Для меня, всё это выглядело необычно,
как только я услышал
слово «децентрализация» и узнал,
что валюта поддерживается сетью,
а не эмиссионным центром,
всё это сразу привлекло мой интерес,
что-то совершенно иное, базирующееся
на том, о чём я знал немного. А именно
currencies at that time.  What it meant
об альтернативных валютах.
for people who are libertarians in
particular is that the government
couldn't come in and shutdown a server
and end Bitcoin, it would have to shut
down the entire internet or turn off the
electricity grid to stop Bitcoin.  And
so that was really attractive to
people who are worried about these types
of things. Many of the early Bitcoin
enthusiasts were libertarians who saw
Bitcoin
as the ultimate remedy for state
intervention.  This was also what
attracted Roger Ver to Bitcoin.  In his
early 20s, he was a candidate for the
Libertarian Party in California.  But
during his campaign, he was sentenced to
10 months in prison for trafficking
illegal fireworks.  According to him, this
was a political case brought by people
who opposed his ideas. I have a two
Bitcoin related gears.  I have the Bitcoin.
org,
and I have the Blockchain.info,
Bitcoin Blockchain logo.
— Do you think it was a
political case?
— There's no doubt in my
mind, whatsoever.  And, in fact, even at one
of the pre-trial conference things with
the ATF agents, my attorney and the U.S.
attorney.  My attorney was saying "Hey, these
are store-bought firecrackers we sold on
eBay.  We can pay a fine.  Do some
community service and you're done with this."
There's no reason to destroy my life
over and send me to prison and make me
a felon.  And the U.S. attorney at that
point was kind of nodding his head like
that sounds reasonable.  The ATF agent
literally pounded his hand on the table
and shouted, "But you didn't hear the
things that he said," which I think summed
up very clearly.  They weren't mad about
anything that I had done.  They're mad
about the things that I had said because
the ideas that I'm trying to spread are
subversive to the state.  I did 10 months
in federal prison and I was scared of
the U.S. government.  The moment I was
allowed to leave the U.S., I left.  And I
haven't lived there ever since.  And they
have what's called the Exit Tax.  So, at the
time you announced you're a United States
citizen, they tax you on your entire net
worth that capital gains tax rates and
you have to pay them that money
otherwise they'll probably either send
you to jail or at the very least not
ever let you back in the country ever
again.  If you think about it, it's not all
that different than slaves from the
past having to buy their freedom from
the plantation owner.
— Money creation by
the state is sort of connected to state
aggression for you, right?
— In my line of
thinking as if you or I create
counterfeit euros or print euros or
dollars or yen, we would go to jail for
counterfeiting because it's destructive
to the economy.  By counterfeiting dollars,
it's stealing from everybody else in the
economy that has money.  When governments
do the exact same thing, it has the exact
same negative effects.  The only
difference is they call it fancy names
like quantitative easing or economic
stimulus but it's destructive for the
exact same reasons.
My hobby growing up and in high school
and since has been studying economics.
And the more you study economics, the
more you realize that all these
government interventions in the economy
prevent the world from becoming as
wealthy and prosperous as it otherwise
would become.  And suddenly now we have
this tool that separates money from
state like everybody today thinks that
separating church and state.  Yeah, of course,
they should be separated.  But a couple
100 years ago, it was heresy:
just hit that church the state should be
separated.  And today, it sounds maybe a
little bit crazy to say that money and
state should be separated.  But I think in
another decade or two, people are going
to think, "Oh, what the heck were we
thinking letting governments be in
charge of money that cost so many
problems in so many misallocations of
resources around the world?"  Of course,
Bitcoin is better.
— Okay.
Thank you.
Why is the governments and banks
monopoly on money creation seen as
undesirable?  In his whitepaper, Satoshi
Nakamoto didn't express his opinion on
this.  But it does seem that he wanted
Bitcoins to appreciate rather than
depreciate unlike money.  He programmed
Bitcoin in such a way that there's a
maximum of 21 million Bitcoins to be
mined.  Bitcoins weren't meant to resemble
money but gold.  In November 2013, this
dream became reality when one Bitcoin
was worth an ounce of gold.  The Bitcoin
code itself has never been hacked.  But in
2014, the customer data of Mt. Gox, an
online exchange office, was stolen by
hackers causing the Bitcoin exchange
rate to plummet.
At the Financial Times in London,
journalist Izabella Kaminska has been
critically following the Bitcoin
exchange rate and community since the
very beginning.
— I've always been a geek
about finance and I've always been a
geek about how the system works.  So, like
the really boring nuts and bolts, the
plumbing of the system.  And I think in
2008, it was the first time we all really
fought actually.  Not only is the system
as it as we know it possibly crumbling,
there might be opportunities for new
systems to come up as a result of it.
— Yeah, exactly.
— Why?  Yes, I guess I start writing
about it again around here, 2012.  And then
we had the first little rally and then
this is also clasp.  This is very
reminiscent to the classic bubble, so.
So, you see this
is the famous bubble chart which has
take off first seller of bear traps as the
first little micro
mini dump.  And you go to the new total
bubble, then it crashes, and it's a bit of
like a return.  People think maybe it's
going to come back and then it crashes
again and then it gets back to a more
realistic trajectory.  And you'll see that
that really is very reminiscent to what
we've seen here.  What everyone is really
wondering is will we see a consolidation
of this price or will it recover
somewhat or will it go completely to
zero.  And we're really--
— What do you think?
I think what's best for Bitcoin is
actually if it just stays stable so
everybody agrees volatility is currently
the biggest enemy of Bitcoin.
— Satoshi's
dream, what would that be? The
paper doesn't really say what his big
dream was.  He just wanted an efficient
mechanism that was cheap.  But in terms of
what I think people have projected his
vision as being is this world where we
all are our own
bank.  We don't have to depend on any
intermediary.  And banks are gone in the
current economy because of the way our
system is structured if I decide to hold
my dollars, I'm usually holding them in
an institution that is using them as a
means of capital raising and they will
be lending them out.  So, my money even
though I'm saving, that saving is going
into an investment somewhere else being
done by a bank, et cetera.  And it's helping to
grow the economy.
So, my saving doesn't disadvantage the
economy.  But in Bitcoin, there isn't that
opportunity.  So hoarded Bitcoin is
a hoarded Bitcoin.  It's totally idle.
It has no interest, it has no yield; it is
simply sitting there, doing nothing, and
yet the person who holds on to it thinks
they have a right to future income flow
as if they have been invested.
— When
the line was flat, people like massively
bought in or mined Bitcoins.  And they are
now like multi-millionaire, billionaires.
They're the new 1%.  They're the 1% of the
Bitcoin economy which again goes against
the whole democratization side of the
argument.  Because really, you're not
democratizing the economy, you're just
transferring the power from the existing
elite to a new elite.
The fact that a few
early Bitcoin miners and investors are
now multimillionaires is reminiscent of
the current banking system in which
bankers are accused of personal
enrichment.
So I got this degree in international
development.  And as I was with my dog on
his Hill and I was like, "Yeah, what could
I do?  I would go try and work in something like, say,
East Africa.  I could try to go and explore
economies there and see what's happening
which I things."  And I was like
"Why don't I just try and break into the
financial sector in London?  Thought it would
actually be really, really fascinating.
That'd be really amazing."  And then once I
had that thoughts, I couldn't -- I mean, I
just became obsessed with this idea.
Brett Scott is the author of the book,
Hacking the Future of Money, about
reforming the financial sector to
immerse himself in the system he
criticized he worked for two years as a
broker in the city of London.
— We're now
in the city.  We just passed the border
checkin.
— Huh.  Yeah.
— There's check ins marked at the
boundaries of the City of London.
— It's
the financial district.
Cut off of my hair, I bought my first
suit.  Interestingly enough, I had two
interviews with Lehman Brothers
literally weeks before they went bust.
And I remember being up in the, sort of, like the 35th
floor or something.  And the guy was like
"I know everything's fine, everything's
fine.
Don't believe the stories
you've seen in the press about us."  And then
they went under.  "If you created an entire
society that was reliance on Bitcoin, yeah,
you'd have massive problems with
inequality."  But it's very important
in that it's forms a kind of counter
power to the existing bank payment
system.  So, while I can critique Bitcoin
as much as you want, I'm always
aware that's the existing
bank system is highly flawed and I
lacked the fact that this exists as an
alternative.  What's happening right now
in a lot of the banking scene is just move
towards -- it's called a cashless society.
But if you think what would that actually
means, it means every single payment that
you undertake has to go via a commercial
bank.  Now, that means every single
transaction you ever do will be
monitored and recorded in a database
somewhere.  It means you'll always be
giving fees to various credit
card companies and so on.  So, there's
potential achievements of
surveillance.  There's all sorts of
problems that come with a cashless
society.  In that world something like
Bitcoin, which is an electronic version
of cash or electronic full of, I guess, an
electronic equivalent to cash, becomes
quite important.
So St. Paul's Cathedral across there,
which is
where the Occupy movement set up camp
in London and they were there for a long time.  They
tried to occupy the London Stock
Exchange, but weren't able to get in, so they
show to St. Paul's instead.
— You think of
Bitcoin and the whole movement being as
a sort of better form of Occupy?
— It's a
different form of Occupy.  Maybe it's a
follow-on from the Occupy
movement in some ways.
— Bitcoin as a form
of protest against the current banking
system is propagated in the Netherlands
by three Bitcoin enthusiasts who have
created an app called Bitcasa and who
are now trying to convince all retailers
in Arnhem to accept Bitcoins.
van der Meijde: (Speaking Foreign Language) When I talk to people about how Bitcoin works, at first they're surprised. They think it's very special.  But these people also don't have a clue how the current system works.  Because it's pretty hard to believe how it works.
Rogier Eijkelhof:       (Speaking Foreign Language) People feel a lot of resistance, or they even deny that there are a few companies that create all the money and that people, companies, and even governments borrow it from these banks.  But these banks literally create it out of thin air, so that's very wrong.
Annet de Boer:          (Speaking Foreign Language) This is the map of Arnhem.  This is the center, and here's the fashion quarter.  You can see that the Bitcoin acceptors are spread out, but mostly in the center there's a huge number of Bitcoin acceptors.
Unidentified male:     (Speaking Foreign Language) You can spend a fun week here without euros?
Annet de Boer:          (Speaking Foreign Language) Yes, you can have a lot of fun.  You can spend the night, there are leisure activities like the wine museum, bowling.
van der Meijde: (Speaking Foreign Language) We've already had several Bitcoin tourists who came to Arnhem because we started something here that allows you to have a great weekend, while only spending Bitcoins.
Unidentified male:    (Speaking Foreign Language) Not so many payments yet, right?
Unidentified male:     (Speaking Foreign Language) No, not so many.  A couple of people have used Bitcoins, but--
Unidentified male:    (Speaking Foreign Language) But there could be more.
Unidentified male:    (Speaking Foreign Language) Definitely.  I prefer Bitcoins to debit card payments, but we'll see.  Everyone's so crazy about debit cards, but everybody has a smartphone.  And banks just take too much money for everything.  So you have to rent or buy a terminal, you have to buy bundles, the deposits, all those things together just cost too much money.
Unidentified male:     (Speaking Foreign Language) As an entrepreneur, you get Bitcoins but through the BitKassa system you get paid in euros?
Unidentified male:     (Speaking Foreign Language) Yeah.
Unidentified male:     (Speaking Foreign Language) And when would you decide to keep the Bitcoins and not change them into euros?
Unidentified male:     (Speaking Foreign Language) If there's really a tipping point.  When you really start noticing a snowball effect, which you see it grow and you think, "This is going to work."  And then we just continue.
van der Meijde: (Speaking Foreign Language) These students will all receive Bitcoins. Tonight, we'll hand them out.  Yes?  I'll send the Bitcoins now.  They should all arrive at the same time.  They're on their way.
Unidentified male:    (Speaking Foreign Language) Yes, I've got it.  12.79.
van der Meijde: (Speaking Foreign Language) 12.79?
Unidentified male:    (Speaking Foreign Language) Yes.
Unidentified male:    (Speaking Foreign Language) 63,000 Bitcoins.
van der Meijde: (Speaking Foreign Language) How is it different from the euro, you think?
Unidentified male:    (Speaking Foreign Language) It goes up and down much more.
van der Meijde: (Speaking Foreign Language) The exchange rate?
Unidentified male:    (Speaking Foreign Language) Yes.
Unidentified male:    (Speaking Foreign Language) You don't really know what you have.  For instance, we just got 12.69, but now it's 12.72.
Beside the ease of use, the Arnhem
students have also noticed a less
pleasant quality to Bitcoins.
The fluctuating exchange rate compared
to other currencies which could make a
beer a couple of cents cheaper or more
expensive between ordering and serving.
So Bitcoin in my mind definition is
not money.  The key to something being
money in my opinion is that it's a
widely used unit of account meaning that
goods and services are priced in it.  So
when you go to the coffee shop you see
something priced in Bitcoin.  That's not
true.
There are coffee shops where there are
prices in Bitcoin, but that price is
changing constantly based on the
currency it's linked to.  So, the pound, for
example, here in England lost 20% of its
value recently.  But the price of coffee
didn't change, it was still 99p.
That's what it means to be a unit of
account and Bitcoin is not that.  The
price adjusts based on its exchange rate
continuously.
— Do you see Bitcoin as a
form of money or as a digital gold?
— So I
see gold as money.  And I see Bitcoin as
having all the same properties of gold
with one property that -- actually couple
properties are even better.  So, gold is
kind of hard to divide.  Bitcoin divides
down to eight decimal points instantly
super easily.
Gold is really, really difficult to
transport.  If I want to transport gold
from here to Moscow, it'll cost a bunch
of money to do that and it's dangerous,
you have to have armed guards, and who
knows what.  With Bitcoin, I can send Bitcoin
from here to Moscow or to the Holland
instantly just like that basically for
free.  I don't have to pay for a bunch of
armed guards.  It just happens almost like
magic.
— If you ever ask somebody why they
think gold's valuable, can everybody tell
you, they would just give you like weird stories
around ads like a precious metal, isn't it?
It's pretty.  While we think it has
all its intrinsic value, this intrinsic
value of gold has been largely
constructed in people's heads.  It's often
by a shield like association with power,
association with religious figures, and
Bitcoin has potential for similar
types of construction.  You could create
the sense of this almost like a
commodity like token that has no
immediate sort of value to it, but can be
imbued with value.
As more people start to mind, they become
harder and harder to find.  So it's kind
of been -- I correlated to like an arms
race, right.  The guy with the biggest gun
wins at this point.  So, this is the newest
place we've started working on here.
This is a place in the mountains in China.
It's cool and it doesn't rain
that much so we can cool it very efficiently.
How much do you pay for that electricity
on a daily basis?
I'll lend all of my minds together.
We're probably paying about $100,000,
maybe a little bit more.
—A day?
—Yeah.
—You're
paying $100,000 a day?
I'm sorry.  That's per month, I'm sorry.
Okay. Okay. —But Bitcoin in general,
all myself and all my colleagues combined,
it's about a million dollars a day in power.
In power consumption? —Yeah. —And you guys
generate what worth of coins?
We're generating -- of course, it depends
on the price, right.  But --
Uh-huh.  The current market price?
Right.  So, we'll just say for 250.  We'll just put the
price at $250 for easy numbers.
You're finding roughly around 25 Bitcoins
every 10 minutes, so you just take that
and times it by an hour.  So, you're finding
around 150 Bitcoins an hour.  Take that
times 24 and you do that times 250.
Do some practical.  So, we're making about $900,000
per day.  So, a lot of
people ask, "How is that possible?"
And the reality is a lot of the Chinese guys.
They are mining at a negative profit.
One of my friends in Beijing I met him last month.
I met him up again and I asked him,
"Last time I checked, man, your power was
pretty expensive.  Why are you still mining?"
And his only words were, "I can't stop."
"So, what do you mean you can't stop,
you're losing money?"  He's like "Well, I can't.
I have all these pieces
of equipment and I just can't stop."
It's gold fever, right? That's right.
And it's interesting because a lot of
my colleagues don't see it
as a business
subconsciously.  They kind of
get addicted to it and kind of get crazy
about it.
(Speaking Foreign Language) This is the first Bitcoin mine in Changcheng.  Three floors, we're on the first.  On this scale and with this equipment we can mine 20 to 25 Bitcoins a day.  There are 3000 computers here.
Unidentified Male:    (Speaking Foreign Language) Most employees live here while they're working.  Compared to other employees in traditional lines of business, our employees make a lot of money.
Jin Xin:                      (Speaking Foreign Language) This is the room where employees can relax.  They lead a simple, maybe even boring life.  When they're not working, they sleep, read, or play with their mobile phones.
So what was supposed to be a very
democratic system has ended up
concentrating it exactly the same way
that we have seen the bank's concentrate
their business.  So now you have most of
the miners are based in China or most of
the miners are huge server farms that
the average person can't be
a miner anymore in Bitcoin.  It's far,
that the barriers to entry are now really,
really quite expensive that you have to
invest in at least
thousands of dollars of equipment if you
want to be a miner. And a lot of people
who got into the first year of Bitcoin
actually had mental breakdowns.  It was so
beautiful.  It was like you're seeing
some of the most remarkable art
ever for the first time. One of the
qualities that I don't like about the
community is that it's extremely
absolutist.  It's very politically led
and it assumes that it's political ideology
is the correct one and it kind of
frosts its political ideology on everybody
else.
So, say I don't want political
ideology when I'm paying for my coffee.
I just want a payment network that works
and that allows me to benefit from
smooth transaction.
Lots of paper money.
So this is a receipt and this is my
public address and private key.
You got it covered for us so we cannot film it.
That's right.
Over the past two years, new members are
increasingly joining the Bitcoin
community not for ideological reasons
but for practical ones. --In Kiev, there are
some protests happening so people start
using social media to share their QR code.
Within a matter of days, they
automatically had $15,000
in their wallets from
sympathizers to the protest that money
was transferred from around the world.
It's an incredibly powerful example because
today I spent seven years in Nicaragua
and today I still cannot use PayPal
to transfer money to my friends in
Nicaragua. —Whether or not Bitcoin will be
worth millions isn't the main question
for many computer scientists, investors
and hackers.  To them, Satoshi Nakamoto's
real invention is the Blockchain
technology, a global open ledger which
can be used to share much more than just
money.
You may think that Bitcoin is just
another way to pay for a cup of coffee,
but it's not.  Bitcoin is just the
denomination used to pay the toll to put
stuff on this global ledger.
Now if you think about it, time stamp
recordings of deaths, births, property
transactions, votes, this is the entire
fabric of our civilization which makes
the Blockchain one of the most profound
human innovations of our time because
having a massive global ledger as a
public utility can completely reorganize
the way that we run our societies.
Fundamentally, Blockchain is a database
sort of mechanism and it's a standard,
it's a protocol.  And one of the problems
we have in an increasingly globalized
system is that everyone is operating
their systems on their own local
standards.  And getting people to do
everything in a uniform way that
benefits all of us like
bringing
in the metric system.  That is really,
really hard.  Blockchain offers
an opportunity to start this new exciting
technological industry from a
standard that is globalized
and potentially uniform.  So I see the
potential that way. —The decentralized
Blockchain makes it possible to share
data publicly without a single party
controlling the system.  In the Blockchain,
all participants in the network are equal.
Maybe inventor Satoshi Nakamoto saw
Bitcoin as just the first experiment
with this form of digital democracy.
I think Blockchain technology is really
authentically fascinating.  I think
it's anybody who ignores it and in (Inaudible 00:43:28)
is probably making a mistake.
I think it's definitely not going to get
smaller.
But to this day, the true identity of the
architect behind this revolutionary
technology remains a mystery.
We can't ask Satoshi questions, which is
really frustrating, right.  But it's also
again part of I think the magic of
Bitcoin is that we can all kind
of imagine this technology for
as we see it rather than just as
Satoshi did.  So it could be used in
this way even if Satoshi didn't intended
to be this widely
worldwide distributed thing.  I think
Satoshi probably did,
but it still could be that.  And we can
make it that. —Satoshi around here
somewhere in Tokyo?
Yeah.  I think I see him right there.
Oh, that's a question I get a lot actually.
A lot of people have asked me who
Satoshi is since I got in so early.
I think I've got a pretty good idea, but I
like to keep that one close to my chest, so.
Why, I mean, tell me? —Because I'm not 100%
certain.  And the reality is it
doesn't really matter, right.  It doesn't
matter who Satoshi is because now it's
kind of grown beyond like a pet project, right.
But what I mean, Satoshi
owns how much, how many coins? —I think he's
got about 500,000 locked up. —With his
Blockchain technology, inventor Satoshi
Nakamoto has completely relinquished his
control of Bitcoin.  But he does own
120th of all Bitcoins himself.  So if
one day, Bitcoin does become widely
accepted as a currency he will be one of
the richest people on earth. —People might
find that scary, a new currency or system
based on an inventor who owns already,
well, 120th of all the currency invented?
Yeah. —Isn't that a problem?
Satoshi invented one of the most
important inventions in the entire
history of humankind.  That's going
to improve the lives of everybody on the
planet for the better.  If he had half of
all the Bitcoins, he would still deserve it.
Who do you think Satoshi is? —I think
it's probably a band of people who
decided that a nom de plume was the best
way to go precisely because if it did
take off, there would be too many
consequences for a individual, one person,
or even a group of people.  And from my
perspective, you never make a move of
this sort without a myth.  You need a sort
of foundation myth.  Every good sort of
system of power has a foundation myth.
And it's always best if the
leader is either anonymous or aloof or
in some way distant from the public
because you have to create a sort of
mythology around him.  And because Satoshi
nobody knows he is,
this -- if we knew who he was it
would almost ruin
the whole thing for everybody, I think.
Why did he disappear, you think?
He undermined the ability of every single
government on the entire planet to
control the money supply.  And that's how
every single government in the world is
controlling their citizens and their
economies today.  And he just basically
knocked their feet right out
from under them with the invention of
Bitcoin.  And I'm sure that's going to
make a lot of people who want to control
other people by force.
I'm really, really upset.  So, yeah, I think
it's really, really smart for him to have
disappeared.  And for me, it probably
would have been smarter for me to keep
quiet, too, but Bitcoins too exciting for me
to stay quiet about.
I think a lot of people are under
estimating the way in which Bitcoin and
the Blockchain are going to change
the power structures in society in general.
I mean, I grew up in the U.S. and
I see all these people like, yeah,
nuke everybody in the Middle East and kill
them all.  And then they have the former
Secretary of State Madeleine Albright on
60 Minutes, one of the most popular news
shows in the U.S. and they asked her,
they said like, there's reports that more than
half a million Iraqi children have died
as a direct result of U.S. sanctions.
And she looks back at her with a straight
face and she goes, "It was a really tough
decision, but I think that it was worth
it."
Worth?  Murdering half a million kids
because of what the government did?  And I
apologized for crying, but it just
disgusts me from my core when I see
government people murdering people
around the world.  It's not just
theoretical these were real people with
real lives.
And it's real people and Bitcoin has the
power to undermine everything
they're doing to people around the world.  And I'm
sorry for shouting, but it just disgusts
me what these people in government do.
And they do it through central banking and
through the control of the money supply
and Bitcoin takes that away from them.
(END OF AUDIO)